Let's start this section by understanding
what asynchronous JavaScript actually is,
and also learn about the most popular use cases
of asynchronous JavaScript,
which is basically to make so-called Ajax calls to APIs.
Now, to understand
what asynchronous JavaScript code actually is,
we first need to understand what synchronous code is.
So basically the opposite of asynchronous.
So most of the codes
that we've been writing so far in the course
has been synchronous code,
and synchronous simply means
that the code is executed line by line,
in the exact order of execution
that we defined in our code,
just like in this small example.
So as the first line of code is reached in the execution,
it is simply executed in the execution of thread.
Now don't worry about this execution of thread.
It's not important here,
it's just to make a point of synchronous
versus asynchronous code,
as you will see in the next slide.
All you need to know is that the execution of thread
is part of the execution context,
which does actually execute the code
in the computer's processor.
But anyway, then the next line of code is executed
and then the next one, all in sequence.
So each line of code always waits
for the previous line to finish execution.
Now this can create problems when one line of code
takes a long time to run.
For example, in this current line of code,
we have an alert statement,
which creates this alert window.
Now, as we've experienced in the past,
this alert window will block the code execution, right?
So nothing will happen on the page
until we click that OK Button.
And only then,
the code can continue executing.
And so the alert statement is a perfect example
of a long running operation,
which blocks execution of the code.
So again, only after we click Okay,
the window disappears
and the next line can run.
So this is hopefully a nice illustration
of the problem with synchronous code.
Now, most of the time synchronous code is fine
and makes perfect sense.
But imagine that execution would have to wait
for example, for a five second timer to finish.
That would just be terrible, right?
Because meanwhile,
nothing on the page would work
during these five seconds.
And so that's where asynchronous code
comes into play.
So this example contains the five-second timer
that I just mentioned.
And if you want,
you can pause the video here for a minute
and analyze this code before we move on.
Now, anyway, the first line of code
is still synchronous here,
and we also move to the second line
in a synchronous way.
But here we encountered the set timeout function,
which will basically start a timer in an asynchronous way.
So this means that the timer
will essentially run in the background
without preventing the main code from executing.
We also register a callback function,
which will not be executed now,
but only after the timer has finished running.
And we have actually already done this many times
before in practice, right?
Now this callback function
that I just mentioned is asynchronous JavaScript.
And it is asynchronous
because it's only going to be executed after a task
that is running in the background finishes execution.
And in this case, that is the timer.
So this callback that we just talked about is registered,
and then we immediately move on to the next line.
So the main code is not being blocked
and execution does not wait for the asynchronous timer
to finish its work.
And that's the big difference between synchronous
and asynchronous code.
So previously we had to wait for the user to click
on the alert window to continue execution.
And again, that's because
alert is blocking synchronous code,
but now with this timer,
the callback is actually asynchronous.
And so it's only going to be executed
after the timer has finished.
And so therefore we say,
that it's non-blocking
because in the meantime,
the rest of the code can keep running normally.
Now, when the timer finally finishes after five seconds,
the callback function will finally be executed as well.
So you'll see that this callback
runs after all the other code,
even though in the code,
it doesn't appear at the end.
And so basically an action was deferred
into the future here
in order to make the code non-blocking.
And actually we already saw this behavior happening before
when we first learned about timers,
we just didn't know that this is called asynchronous
and non-blocking code.
So in summary, asynchronous programming
is all about coordinating
the behavior of our program
over a certain period of time.
And this is essential to understand.
So asynchronous literally means
not occurring at the same time.
And so that's what asynchronous programming is all about.
All right.
Now, as we saw in this example,
we need a callback function to implement
this asynchronous behavior, right?
However, that does not mean that callback functions
automatically make code asynchronous.
That is just not the case, okay?
For example, the Array map method
accepts a callback function as well,
but that doesn't make the code asynchronous.
Only certain functions such as set timeout
work in an asynchronous way.
We just have to know which ones do
and which ones don't, okay?
But please understand this very important fact
that callback functions alone
do not make code asynchronous,
that's essential to keep in mind.
But anyway, in order to really understand this,
let's see another example.
So this example is about loading an image.
So the first two lines run in a synchronous way,
one after the other.
Now in the second line,
we set the source attribute of the image
that we selected in the first line.
And this operation is actually asynchronous.
So setting the source attribute of any image
is essentially loading an image in the background
while the rest of the code can keep running.
And this makes sense, right?
Imagine that it's a huge image,
we wouldn't want our entire code
to wait for the image to load.
And that's why setting the source attribute
was implemented in JavaScript
in an asynchronous way.
Now, once the image has finished loading,
a load event will automatically be emitted by JavaScript.
And so we can then listen for that event
in order to act on it.
Listening for the load event
is exactly what we do here
in the next line as well.
So here we use add event listener
and to register a callback function
for the load event.
So just like in the previous example,
we provide a callback function that will be executed
once the image has been loaded
and not right away,
because again, all this code is non-blocking.
So instead of blocking,
execution moves on right
to the next line immediately.
Then once the image is completely loaded,
it's displayed on the webpage
and the load event is admitted.
And since we're listening for that event,
our callback function is finally executed.
So once more,
we deferred an action into the future
making the code asynchronous and non-blocking.
All right.
And so now at this point,
I believe that you have a pretty good understanding
of asynchronous code.
There's just one more important thing
that I need to mention
which is the fact that event listeners alone
do not make code asynchronous,
just like callback functions alone,
do also not make code asynchronous.
For example, an event listener
listening for a click on a button
is not doing any work in the background.
It's simply waiting for a click to happen,
but it's not doing anything.
And so there is no asynchronous behavior involved at all.
Now what makes this code example asynchronous
is simply the fact that the image
is loading asynchronously in the background,
but not the fact that we are listening
for the load events to happen.
So what matters is the asynchronous behavior of a task,
like running a timer
or loading an image.
And there are more examples
of asynchronous behavior in JavaScript
like the Geolocation API that we used before,
or Ajax calls.
And Ajax calls are probably the most important use case
of asynchronous JavaScript.
And so let's see what Ajax is all about.
So Ajax stands for asynchronous JavaScript and XML,
and basically it allows us to communicate
with remote web servers in an asynchronous way.
Now in practice,
we make Ajax calls in our code
in order to request some data
from a web server dynamically.
So without reloading the page
so that we can use that data in our application dynamically.
For example, right in the next video,
we're going to make Ajax calls
to request data about countries.
And we can then use that data about countries
to build a small application
that shows us information about the country
that we're currently in.
And the possibilities and use cases are endless,
but more about that in the next slide.
For now, let's quickly understand how Ajax works.
So let's say that we have our JavaScript application
running in the browser,
which is also called the Client.
And we want the application to get some data
from a web server.
And let's say the data about countries
that I was talking about earlier.
So with Ajax,
we can do an HTTP request to the server,
which has this data.
And the server will then set back a response
containing that data that we requested.
And this back and forth between Client and server
all happens asynchronously in the background,
just the way we learned before.
And there can even be different types of requests,
like get requests to receive data
or post requests to send data to a server.
But there is a whole lecture about this a bit later
to really show you how it all works in detail.
Now, when we're asking a server to send us some data,
this server usually contains a web API.
And this API is the one that has the data
that we're asking for.
So an API is something pretty important,
and so let's now see what an API
and web APIs actually are.
So first of all,
API stands for Application Programming Interface.
Now in general terms,
and on the very high level of obstruction,
an API is basically a piece of software
that can be used by another piece of software
in order to basically allow applications
to talk to each other
and exchange information.
And that's true not only for web development and JavaScript,
but for programming in general.
Now in JavaScript and web development,
there are countless types of APIs,
like the DOM API
or the Geolocation API
that we have been using.
So these are called APIs
because they are a self-contained piece of software
that allow other pieces of software
to interact with them.
For example, our Mapty application
that we built in the previous section.
Also, we can always implement
a small and simple API in a class
where we make some methods available
as a public interface.
Remember?
So again, objects made from a class
can be seen as self-contained
encapsulated pieces of software
that other pieces of software can interact with.
And so that fits the definition of API, right?
But now let's talk about the important type of API
that we are actually interested in
when we use Ajax.
And that are APIs
that I like to call Online APIs.
So an online API
is essentially an application running on a web server,
which receives requests for data,
then retrieves this data from some database
and then sends it back to the client.
So just as we saw in the last slide, right?
Now, when building applications in practice,
we simply call these online APIs, API,
and many people will also call these APIs, Web APIs,
or again, just simply API.
So the term Online API is actually a term
that I came up with myself
because the term Web API
is actually also used for other things.
Now, of course we can build or own Online APIs,
but that requires back-end development.
So development with servers and databases
and all that.
And this is something really interesting
that you can learn after this course,
and I actually have a course on Node.js myself,
that you can check out if you're interested.
But anyway, for now,
we are interested in using 3rd-party APIs.
So APIs that other developers make available for us
most of the times for free.
So let's now imagine
that you're building a traveling application,
and you have a database with different destinations
and tours that you're offering.
So on your own server,
you could build your own API
that can receive requests
from your front end application in JavaScript
and send back the results.
So that would be your own API
hosted on your own server.
But that alone would probably not be enough
to build a complete application.
And so you could also use some 3rd-party APIs.
And there are really APIs for everything.
So in our example, travel application,
you could use an API
to get weather data in your destinations,
data about the destination countries themselves,
data about flights,
about currency conversion.
And you could even use APIs
to send emails or text messages
or embed Google maps into your applications.
So as you see,
the possibilities are really endless with APIs,
and we can even say that APIs
is what made the modern web as you know it
possibly in the first place.
So using APIs in JavaScript is super popular
and everyone does it all the time,
and so that's why I'm explaining you all these details.
Okay.
But now just to finish,
let's quickly talk about API data formats.
So Ajax stands for asynchronous JavaScript and XML.
Remember?
So the X there stands for XML
and XML is a data format,
which used to be widely used
to transmit data on the web.
However, these days
basically no API uses XML data anymore.
The term Ajax is just an old name
that got very popular back in the day,
and so it's still used today,
even though we don't use XML anymore.
So instead, most APIs these days
use the JSON data format.
So JSON is the most popular data format today
because it's basically just a JavaScript object,
but converted to a string.
And so therefore,
it's very easy to send across the web
and also to use in JavaScript
once the data arrives.
All right.
So, now that we know what asynchronous JavaScript is,
and also what Ajax and APIs are,
let's finally use all this in practice
and make our very first Ajax call
in the next video.